So in this short video, I'm going to
give an example of how you can use
the critical path method to identify
the time frame for a given project.
It's important to understand the critical
path method when you're working in software
development and whether you're working
within a project or part of a project team.
So you can actually physically map out the
time frames for that project with a realistic
time scale and fully understand what needs
to be done to achieve the project's aims.
So if we're.
First thing we need to do is look
at what is the critical path method.
So the critical path, it's basically, it's a,
it's a simple method to evaluate and identify
all of the critical steps in order to be able
to identify the time it would take to complete.
The actual project.
It's a very useful project management technique
and it was initiated in the 1950s when a
project with the United States government
was running behind schedule and they
brought this in and it worked effectively.
So what we're going to use as an example for
this is we're going to actually just look
at the critical path for cooking a steak.
Now, it may seem simplified, but again,
this is, I've kept it simple because this
can then be applied to any project, any
task, and it will just give you a, a basic
understanding of the processes involved in
finding the critical path for any given project.
So what we'll start with, we're
looking, we need to grill a steak.
So that's the starting point.
And then we have a branch.
And then we have three items here,
marinate the steak, sauté the
onions and mushrooms, add garnish.
As you can see, these have all
been tagged as non critical tasks.
But by the alternative, you have the light
the grill, put steaks on the grill and
cook till it's to your desired liking.
So medium rare or well done.
Those are all critical
elements within the project.
So we can straight away, we can see
the critical paths within there.
But this doesn't help calculate
the timeframes and that.
So what we need to do then is we need to
actually plan out everything that's involved
in getting from the start to the end.
to grill a steak.
So what you need to do for that is you create a
work breakdown structure document, so it's a WBS.
So as mentioned on the previous
slide, we need to grill a steak.
So the first thing we need to do is there's some
shopping because we need to get the ingredients.
We then need to prepare the food
and we then need to cook the food.
So these are the three elements involved
in overview of a grilling a steak.
So those are all linked together.
You can't do one without the other.
They are all requirements.
So let's look at the shopping.
So we need to buy the onions and mushrooms.
We need to buy the marinade.
We need to buy the steak.
So once we've got all of that,
we then need to prepare the food.
We need to marinate the steaks.
We need to chop the onions and mushrooms,
and then we need to cook the food.
So we need to light the grill,
grill the steaks to your liking.
Sorting the onions and mushrooms.
So those are all of the steps that are
involved in grilling a steak So we've got
a full work breakdown structure there.
We need to go shopping We need to prepare
the food and cook the food and all of
the relevant subtasks for each of those
So now what we need to do is we
need to establish task dependencies.
So what tasks are dependent on each other?
So let's start always begin with a start an icon.
So buy a steak, buy marinade
and buy onions and mushrooms.
So now that we've got all of that, we can
then marinate the steaks, we can then light
the grill, and now we move to another path
because while we've lit the grill, we can then
move on to chopping the onions and mushrooms,
then we can grill the steaks to our liking,
we can then saute the onions and mushrooms.
And as you can see, everything
converges on the finish.
So we're grilling the steaks, the sort
of the onions and mushrooms, we'll
put them together, we're finished.
So as you can see, it's all about
creating the task dependency.
So what task is dependent on, on each other?
So all of those, the marinade, like
the grill, everything's dependent on
the first three, which is buy steak,
buy marinade, buy onions and mushrooms.
And as you can see, Everything
maps across well there.
So one of the things you're going to hear when
you're doing the critical path is terminology.
So you'll mainly hear the terms earliest
finish date and earliest start date.
You may hear the words float and crash.
But what we're going to look at here is instead
of the earliest finish date and the earliest start
date, I'm going to use the time rather than date.
Obviously, it doesn't take days
to create a, to cook a steak.
So we're just going to be looking at time.
So it'll be the earliest finished
time or the earliest start time.
So, but as I mentioned here that this
is a crucial step because the durations
will allow you to identify what the
critical path is for the project.
So it will allow you to find the most important
parts of the path to completing the project.
We need to determine the duration of each task.
So we have the start.
So the earliest start time is zero, the earliest
finish time is zero, and the time to complete.
So all of those stand for earliest start
time, earliest finish time, time to complete.
It's zero.
It's always zero at the start.
So by the stake.
So the earliest start time is zero because
that's the very first task we're doing.
This is just an estimate, but we're,
the earliest finish time is 30 minutes.
It's going to take 30 minutes to go to the
shops, buy the ingredients and get back home.
So we'll start, takes 30 minutes.
So the total time to complete that,
those, that task there is 30 minutes.
We then need to marinate the steaks.
So the earliest start time is 30 minutes
into the project, because I can't do that
until I've got home with the ingredients.
It's going to take 15 minutes, which
is the TTC, total time to complete.
So the earliest finish time is 45
minutes after the project started.
So as you can see, we've
basically looked at there.
I can't start it until I've done the
shopping and it's going to take 15 minutes.
So that adds to the initial time
that it took for the shopping.
So light the grill.
So the earliest start time is 45 minutes.
So I can't do that until
I've marinated the steaks.
So you can see that the earliest finish
time for marinated steaks is the same as the
earliest start time for lighting the grill.
The earliest finish time is 55
because it's going to take 10 minutes.
So that's 10 added to 45 is 55.
So then we need to grill the steaks.
So again, I can't start that until I've finished
lighting the grill, which so the earliest
start time is 55 minutes into the project.
It's going to take 20 minutes
for total time to complete.
So the earliest finish time
is going to be 75 minutes.
So now we'll move over to
the onions and mushrooms.
So The earliest start time for that is 30,
again because I can't start that one until
after I have actually done the chopping.
It's going to take 10 minutes, so the
earliest finish time is 40 minutes.
And sauté the onions and mushrooms, I can't do
that until I've chopped the onions and mushrooms.
So that's going to, earliest
start time is 40 minutes.
I'm going to take 10 minutes, so the
earliest finish time is 50 minutes.
So the total time for that is 50 minutes
and the total time for that is 75 minutes.
So it's going to take 50 minutes
to get to the finish by following
the the bottom path and 75 minutes.
Obviously all tasks have to be
completed to get to the finish point.
So the project's completed.
So what is the critical path in relation to that?
So if we have a look now, The critical path, what
can we utilize to identify the critical path?
So the first part is quite straightforward.
The start to the binding ingredients
is the first part of the critical path.
Then the second part of the
critical path is marinate steaks.
Then light the grill.
Grill steaks to light in total time 75 minutes.
Now the reason why that is the critical
path, and again, this is very simplistic,
is that you want to grill the steak.
The onions and mushrooms and salt
of the onion and mushrooms isn't a,
it's not a matter of requirement.
It's a something that would
be nice to go on the grill.
And the thing being is that because this is taking
75 minutes, that's the critical path in the The
chopping the onions and mushrooms and sorting
the onions and mushrooms only takes 50 minutes.
You have technically 25 minutes float.
So if there were any delays with the critical
path element, you could take some time from
the Saltier and mushrooms and the onions root
and add that to the total grilling time So
you could steal some time from there if you
are going to overrun now I know this is quite
a simplistic one, but it does give you a good
overview of how you would Identify the critical
path and again this can be used for any project.
So why don't you have a think about something
that you do or a little project that you're
involved in and try and estimate the the critical
path and see if it can work for yourself.
There is also a link at the bottom of the
page which will take you and it goes into
a lot more depth and and more detail in
relation to how critical path analysis works.